<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- 
     draft-rfcxml-general-template-standard-00
  
     This template includes examples of the most commonly used features of RFCXML with comments 
     explaining how to customise them. This template can be quickly turned into an I-D by editing 
     the examples provided. Look for [REPLACE], [REPLACE/DELETE], [CHECK] and edit accordingly.
     Note - 'DELETE' means delete the element or attribute, not just the contents.
     
     Documentation is at https://authors.ietf.org/en/templates-and-schemas
-->
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
	<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
	<!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
	<!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
	<!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-stockhammer-msf-urn-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes=""
     updates=""
     submissionType="IETF"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="URN Namespace for MSF">URN Namespace for Metaverse Standards Forum Resources</title>
		<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
		            value="draft-stockhammer-msf-urn-00"/>
		<author fullname="Thomas Stockhammer"
		        initials="T"
		        role="editor"
		        surname="Stockhammer">
			<organization>Qualcomm Germany GmbH</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Anzingerstrasse 17</street>
					<city>Munich</city>
					<code>81671</code>
					<country>DE</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+491725702667</phone>
				<email>tsto@qti.qualcomm.com</email>
				<!-- Can have more than one <email> element -->
				<uri>URI [REPLACE/DELETE]</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date year="2023"/>
		<area>General</area>
		<workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
		<keyword>URN, Metaverse, Registration, Namespace</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>This document describes the Namespace Identifier (NID) 'cablelabs' for Uniform Resource Names (URNs) used to identify resources published by Metaverse Standards Forum. The forum specifies and manages resources that utilize this URN identification model. Example resources include ressources, eXtensible Markup Language (XML) Schemas, classification schemes, XML Document Type Definitions (DTDs), namespaces, style sheets, and other types of resources produced or managed by the Metaverse Standards Forum.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section>
			<name>Introduction</name>
			<t>The Metaverse Standards Forum is a non-profit, member-funded consortium of standards-related organizations, companies, and institutions that are cooperating to foster interoperability for an open and inclusive metaverse. Originally founded in June 2022, the Forum was incorporated in April 2023 to accelerate its mission to enable and promote broad cooperation and coordination over metaverse-related standards activities. The Forum does not itself create standards but instead generates domain and technical reports, use case and requirements recommendations, pilots, testbeds and plugfests, open source tooling, best practices and guidelines, and other data, insights, and visibility to enable standards organizations to accelerate the development and evolution of standards that will be essential to building the metaverse. As part of these efforts, there is a need to specify identifiers in a managed namespace that are unique and persistent.  To ensure that this namespace's uniqueness is absolute, the registration of a specific Uniform Resource Name (URN) [RFC8141] Namespace Identifier (NID) for use by Metaverse Standards Forum is specified in this document, in full conformance with the NID registration process specified in [RFC8141].</t>
			<t>This namespace specification is for a formal namespace.</t>
			<section>
				<name>Terminology</name>
				<table>
					<thead>
						<!-- [REPLACE/DELETE] a table header is optional -->
						<tr>
							<th>Acronym</th>
							<th>Meaning</th>
						</tr>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>MSF</td>
							<td>Metaverse Standards Forum</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<name>URN Specification for Metaverse Standards Forum</name>
			<dl newline="true">
				<!-- Omit newline="true" if you want each definition to start on the same line as the corresponding term -->
				<dt>Namespace ID:</dt>
				<dd>metaverse-standards-org</dd>
				<dt>Registration Information:</dt>
				<dd>registration version number: 1</dd>
				<dt>Declared registrant of the namespace:</dt>
				<dd>Registering organization</dd>
				<dt>Declaration of syntactic structure:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Relevant ancillary documentation:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Identifier uniqueness considerations:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Identifier persistence considerations:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Process of identifier assignment:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Process for identifier resolution:</dt>
				<dd>registration date: 2023-12-25</dd>
				<dt>Rules for lexical equivalence:</dt>
				<dd>No special considerations; the rules for lexical equivalence of [RFC2141] apply.</dd>
				<dt>Conformance with URN syntax:</dt>
				<dd>No special considerations.</dd>
				<dt>Validation mechanism:</dt>
				<dd>None specified.URN assignment will be handled by procedures implemented in support of Metaverse Standards Forum activities.</dd>
				<dt>Scope:</dt>
				<dd>Global</dd>
			</dl>
		</section>
		<section>
			<name>Example</name>
			<t>The following example represents a hypothetical URN that could be assigned by Metaverse Standards Forum:</t>
			<t>urn:metaverse-standards-org:use-case:avatar-call:2023</t>
			<t>This example defines the URN to be used for a usecase defined in the Metaverse Standards Forum. An associated description of the use case is published.</t>
		</section>
		<section>
			<name>Namespace Considerations</name>
			<t>Metaverse Standards Forum develops ressources that may require the use of data models.  URN Namespaces are key constructs to manage the definitions of those data models reliably with persistence and uniqueness.</t>
			<t>The use of URNs should also help specification authors to maintain different versions of URNs and dependencies between URNs across different versions of Metaverse Standards Forum ressources if they so wish.</t>
		</section>
		<section>
			<name>Community Considerations</name>
			<t>Participants involved in the development and usage of Metaverse Standards Forum ressources and Metaverse industry deployments will benefit from the publication of this namespace by providing consistent and reliable names for the XML namespaces, schema locations, and similar identifiers of physical data models published within Metaverse Standards Forum ressources</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="IANA">
			<!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
			<name>IANA Considerations</name>
			<t>This document adds a new entry ("metaverse-standards-org") in the urn-namespaces registry.  This is the defining document.  The entry can be found in the "Uniform Resource Names (URN) Namespaces" registry available from the IANA site (http://www.iana.org) and any associated mirrors.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security">
			<!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
			<name>Security Considerations</name>
			<t>There are no additional security considerations other than those normally associated with the use and resolution of URNs in general, which are described in [RFC1737], [RFC2141], and [RFC3406].</t>
		</section>
		<!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references>
			<name>References</name>
			<references>
				<name>Normative References</name>
				<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
				<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
				<!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
			</references>
		</references>
		<section anchor="Acknowledgements"
		         numbered="false">
			<!-- [REPLACE/DELETE] an Acknowledgements section is optional -->
			<name>Acknowledgements</name>
			<t>The authors wish to thank XXX for their useful comments and suggestions. The authors also acknowledge that the text from [RFC6289] formed the basis for the initial version of this document.</t>
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
